Initial reports suggest a terrorist involvement,
but this morning some intelligence experts
have claimed the incidents may be a stunt.
The first sightings were of UFOs
over the Taj Mahal in India.
They came in just after midnight.
In London this morning,
there were reports of men in historic dress
firing upon police.
POLICEMAN : Down, down, down.
Some religious groups are claiming
events overnight
are a vindication of their teachings.
Do you think it is terrorists?
Terrorists bomb things. This is different.
People didn't believe us. Now they should.
Judgement Day is finally here.
This is the End of Days.
"And I heard but did not understand
"and I said, 'Master, what is the end
of all these things?'
"And he said, 'Go, Daniel, for the things are
closed up and sealed until the end of time."'
Daniel 12, verse 10.
GWEN : Sounds a bit close for comfort.
This machine's on the blink. Keeps losing power.
Sorry, don't let me stop your portents of doom.
Or have you finished?
No. Plenty more where that came from.
Abaddon, the Great Devourer,
who'll lead the world into shadow.
Yeah, thanks, Ianto,
I can do without the superstition.
You people love any story that denies
the randomness of existence.
Thanks. That makes me feel a lot better.
Okay, I've been fielding calls all night,
the government, U NIT, the CIA.
Half the Western world and a good proportion
of the Eastern are all asking the same question.
Is this anything to do with us?
And is it?
I've run a profile on
every reported temporal anomaly
and tracked any physical or temporal pattern.
Shit.
The cracks in time trace back here to the rift.
This city, this H ub, is the centre.
What you're seeing around the world
are ripples and aftershocks.
-The rift is splintering because of you.
-What?
You opened the rift without knowing
what you were doing.
You've caused the temporal cracks to widen.
Time is seeping through.
If it wasn't for me,
you two would still be in the 1940s.
So are we gonna sit around crying into our lattes
or are we going to do something about it?
Bring those who've fallen through time back here,
into the vaults.
And do what with them?
We'll deal with phase one first,
then I'll tell you about phase two.
You can't control time, you can't send them back.
-What are you gonna do?
-We'll think of something !
Hey,
this is not the end of the world.
I'm certain of that.
(COMPUTER BEEPING)
Priority one attendance requested at the hospital.
Mortality rate's gone through the roof.
They're sealing off the area
and designating a hot zone.
-I'll go.
-Tosh, go with him.
No, thanks, I'm fine on my own.
And you'll be even better with me alongside.
Shut up and come on.
Did you have to pick on him in public like that?
All of our actions have consequences.
And all your staff have feelings, Jack, even Owen.
Well, you would know.
He brought you back.
(MOBILE RINGING)
Would you rather be stuck in World War II?
Hello?
Gwen, it's Andy.
Listen, I didn't know who else to call.
(YELLING)
Double murder. Stabbed two blokes in Penarth.
Brutal, it was. No mercy.
What are we supposed to do?
He doesn't speak a word of English.
And he's dressed as a bloody Roman soldier!
He's not dressed as a Roman soldier,
he is a Roman soldier and he's shouting in Latin.
-Only word I could pick out was Gelligaer.
-Gelligaer?
There's a Roman fort out in Gelligaer.
Built around 75 AD.
So he was on his way there,
time splintered and he ends up here.
Excuse me?
H i, any time you feel like talking sense...
-That soldier came through a crack in time.
-He's not serious, is he?
This sort of thing just doesn't happen.
Not in Cardiff.
Just because you can't understand it,
doesn't mean it isn't true.
I know it sounds mad, Andy, but...
All right, Mulder and Scully, say I do believe you,
which I don't, 'cause it's bollocks,
but say I do, how exactly are we meant to
handle a prisoner from 2,000 years ago?
Has he got the same rights as anyone else?
How's this gonna work with the CPS?
We'll take him off your hands.
(YELLING)
Under any other circumstances,
an exuberant Roman soldier
would be my idea of a perfect morning.
Careful, Jack.
Everyone's saying it, you know.
In work, on the streets.
Do you think this is the end of the world?
Oh, Andy, don't be silly. Do you think
the world's gonna end on your shift?
I've seen you use that smile on a lot of people.
-What smile?
-The smile you use to reassure people
when deep down when you know
everything's going to shit.
This was the first one to die.
No ID on her, she just appeared
in the middle of AandE.
Nobody saw her come through the doors,
she didn't register at the desk.
So what happened?
She started coughing up blood,
we moved her into isolation immediately.
An hour or so later, the staff
started presenting similar symptoms.
Which were?
Bite-like bumps on the skin, chills, fever,
headaches, along with black patches on the skin.
Indicating bleeding into the skin
and possibly other organs.
From the staff,
it started spreading to other patients
who'd been in reception when she came in.
These aren't contemporary clothes.
Her teeth aren't exactly modern style, either.
Shit.
As soon as we realised the rate of infection,
we closed down the whole area.
How many others are infected?
-30, maybe 40.
-OWEN : All quarantined off?
We think so.
Have their clothes and
their sheets destroyed immediately.
(PANTING)
-What is it?
-That woman isn't from this century.
More like the 14th.
(STAMMERING) It's the fucking Black Death, Tosh.
She's infected Cardiff AandE with the plague
and it's my fault.
The team are instigating procedures.
The infected will need 30 milligrams
of streptomycin and chloramphenicol
plus two of tetracycline.
That's plague medicine.
Standard issue for bubonic.
Well done, House. That's what you're up against.
So what are you gonna do now?
Well, you're a hospital.
You've got procedures, haven't you?
Yes, but everybody said Torchwood
would sort it out.
What if we get more carriers appearing
out of the blue?
We're working to stop that.
We waited for you !
You've got to stop this!
You've got to do something !
No, you've got to do something.
People are dropping through time,
and they are gonna bring
every disease in history through your doors.
-So you'd better be ready!
-Owen.
You scared enough yet? 'Cause fuck knows I am !
Come on, Tosh !
Make sure they get the medicine.
Call us if things get worse.
How much worse can they get?
Owen?
Owen !
(WOMAN ON PA)
(SPEAKING IN JAPAN ESE)
Tosh. Come on, stop pissing about!
GWEN : If Owen managed to open the rift
to get you and Tosh back,
can't we do the same for these people?
We've still got the Rift Manipulator.
(SCOFFS) There's a world of difference.
We're talking about taking control of time,
not bringing two people back from the past.
Besides, look at the damage Owen caused.
We mess with it further,
we'll put the whole planet in danger.
Have I ever let you down?
MAN : Gwen?
Gwen?
I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
Gwen.
Gwen ! Come on.
H ustle.
JACK: Are you sure it was the same guy?
It was definitely him.
Bilis the caretaker at the dance hall.
That's all he said? Sorry?
What's he got to be sorry for?
Coming through !
(SNARLING)
Thirteen more reports of Weevils on the loose.
We're not gonna keep up at this rate.
-Everything's on the increase.
-Can we stop them from making that noise?
-If you've got any ideas how.
-Maybe they're time-sensitive.
This disturbance may be too much for them.
We're now full in all vaults across all nine levels.
IANTO: Do you want me to activate
the vaults below?
It's just we've never used them
since I've been here.
Do it.
Gwen, maybe you're right.
Let's run a search on your dance hall buddy.
-We need to find him.
-Okay.
(MOANING)
Hello, Ianto.
What do you want? Why are you here?
This isn't happening.
There's only one way to stop this
before things get worse.
People will die, Ianto, thousands of people,
unless you open the rift.
Owen. How was the hospital?
Laugh a bloody minute.
They've got an outbreak of the Black Death.
What? Oh, my God.
Have they got it under control?
Tosh ! How are they coping?
Owen got the place quarantined and organised
treatments for those who've been infected.
Only consolation is it's treatable these days.
But, you know, what happens when
the next carrier comes through, Jack?
Someone carrying smallpox or Ebola
or something from the future
we don't even know about yet,
what do we do then?
Well, it's not doing us any good
standing around speculating.
We need to be prepared.
We're helpless, all we're doing here
is putting sticking plasters on gaping wounds!
What do you suggest?
I suggest you lead us and you tell us
what the instructions are.
-Owen...
-No, come on.
You're all thinking it, too.
You're the big man here.
You keep all the secrets!
Well, now's the time to tell us a few
and tell us how the hell
we're going to get out of this!
You want to know a secret? There is no solution.
I can't fix this.
Because this was never meant to happen.
The first thing you learnt when you joined
Torchwood was don't mess with the rift.
But you disobeyed those orders and now
everything that's happening is down to you.
I only disobeyed instructions to get you back!
-And now people are dying.
-What, so I shouldn't have bothered?
Who the fuck are you anyway?
Jack Harkness? You don't even exist.
We've looked.
So if you're not even a real person,
then why the hell should I follow your orders?
Get out.
-What?
-Get out!
I'm relieving you of your duty.
-No. You can't do that!
-Bollocks you are!
Jack, wait.
You're done here.
What, so that's it?
The whole world is going to shit
and you're gonna fire me?
For God's sake! Both of you !
We need to stick together on this.
If I can't rely on you, if I don't have
your complete trust, you don't belong here.
That goes for the rest of you.
Anyone who agrees with Owen, leave now!
So now we know how it is.
So that leaves me 24 hours
to savour the good times.
What are you talking about?
Think about it, Gwen.
Nobody leaves this place intact.
Some time in the next 24 hours,
I get retconned.
All my memories erased.
I don't know where or when, but he'll get me.
Jack, this has gone far enough.
Well, I guess this is goodbye.
Good luck with the end of the world.
I would say thanks for the memories.
Jack, for God's sake!
IANTO: Okay, guys, Bilis' shop is coming up
20 metres on your left.
Wow.
Some of this stuff must go back centuries.
He scavenges antique pieces from the past,
brings them here, sells them for a profit.
Not a bad business plan.
We all have to earn a living.
-JACK: You're from 1941.
-As you were. Hello, again.
How can you be in two time zones at once?
I can step across eras,
like you'd walk into another room.
At first, it was the most incredible gift.
Now I know the reality.
It's a curse.
Why?
I can see the whole of history,
but I don't belong anywhere within it.
So, your return to this time had a price.
Time's splintering.
This city exists on a rift in time.
The only way to make it right
is to fully open that rift.
Let it suck back what fell through.
-No way. It's too dangerous.
-Can we even do that?
Of course you can. Isn't that right, Captain?
-Jack?
-You've seen what happened.
If we open that rift fully,
millions of lives will be at risk.
And yet if you don't, more will fall through.
Lives will be lost.
(LAUGHING)
-You know so much, you're coming back with us.
-I'm sorry.
Damn it!
Trace the temporal activity round this location.
We need to find out where he is. Come on.
(WHISPERING) Gwen.
I am not your enemy.
In the cells, why did you say you were sorry?
Sometimes it's better to live in ignorance,
unless...
Do you really want to know?
Know what?
Hold my hands. I'll show you.
-Okay.
-Only if you're sure.
I'm sure.
(GASPING)
I'm sorry.
-What did you just show me?
-The future.
What took you so long?
Gwen?
Gwen !
Is that you?
Yeah.
It's me.
(LAUGHS)
-You're cleaning the oven !
-Aye, somebody got to, love.
We got to go.
-Why, what's happened?
-We've got to go, that's all.
-Let me finish here first.
-Rhys, we've got to go now!
Oh, here we go again, look,
always a hurry with you,
ever since you started that bloody job...
I'm sorry.
(TECH NO MUSIC PLAYING)
WOMAN : Owen.
Owen.
(GASPS) No!
Jesus. Diane.
-Oh, Jesus.
-I'm lost, Owen.
I can touch you. I don't understand.
-Where did you end up?
-Please, bring me back, Owen.
-You can do that, can't you?
-I don't know.
-Everything's out of sync.
-Please.
Please, bring me back. Open the rift.
Do you want another drink there, mate?
Whoa, whoa, take it easy.
What's going on?
Am I dreaming?
This is where I work.
-You work in a prison?
-These are just the cells.
You locked me in a cell?
What the hell are you playing at?
I was just trying to keep you safe.
-I was safe at home!
-No, you weren't.
You really weren't.
Listen here, Gwen,
you better tell me exactly what's going on.
'Cause I've taken some shit
over the past few months.
-I mean, what's all this?
-Rhys, listen to me, I need you to trust me.
Okay, it may not seem like it at the moment,
but I am just trying to take care of you.
I love you, sweetheart.
(MU FFLED GROANING)
What the hell was that?
Just try and relax and I'll come back for you.
What do you mean?
Hey, you're not going to leave me down here!
-I'm sorry.
-Gwen !
Gwen !
-I'm sorry.
-Shit!
-Did he wake up?
-Yeah. Yeah, he did.
Tosh, can you bring up the CCTV of the vaults?
Just leave it on the screen,
I know it sounds crazy but...
Sure, no problem.
Thank you, for helping me bring him here.
I can't understand how
Bilis was able to show you that vision.
It was so real, Tosh. I was in my flat.
It smelt like my flat,
it had all the sounds of my flat.
I touched the blood.
I can still feel it on my hands. Rhys' blood.
It's not gonna happen.
Come on, there's still work to be done.
IANTO: What's going on?
TOSHIKO: We've got a security breach.
(ALARM BLARING)
All right, nobody panic.
Rhys!
Oh, do you work here?
I'm Rhys, Gwen's boyfriend.
No! Rhys, please, please, God !
Please, God !
No!
We can bring... We can bring him back!
-There's nothing we can do.
-Yes, there is!
My boy, what am I gonna do?
What am I going to do?
(SCREAMING)
No!
I'll have to tell his family.
IANTO: We'll deal with it.
The way you dealt with that porter
first time I met you.
No, you won't deal with him, Ianto.
Gwen, I'm so sorry.
You never even met him.
This is what happens here.
We all end up alone.
Not me.
No way.
You bring him back.
-No.
-The resurrection gauntlet...
Was destroyed.
-We've got to have something else.
-I said no.
No, there's something wrong with time
so we can go back
-to the moment, to the very moment...
-Gwen.
Well, there's got to be something that you can do
otherwise what's the fucking point of you?
You, you bring him back! You bring him back!
Bring him to me!
You bring him back!
Do you understand me, Jack fucking Harkness?
-Do you?
-I'm so sorry.
I'm sorry.
(SOBBING)
Oh, shit.
-What happened?
-You came back!
Are you all right? You okay? Are you all right?
Don't touch me!
How many other people have got to suffer?
I'm gonna fix this.
I'm opening the rift.
Make sure you stop him.
No.
We're gonna help him.
Bilis was right. He said, "Open the rift
and everything goes back to normal."
Owen's right. I'm going to get Rhys back.
-Gwen.
-No!
Gwen !
Enter Emergency Protocol One.
Out of the way, I'll do this.
(ALARM BLARING)
Get away from the computer, Gwen.
This is a trap. All these cracks
around the world, they're diversions.
This is what Bilis wants.
What are you afraid of, Jack?
Rhea Silva.
I said move.
-What the hell are you doing?
-Final warning.
Come on, Jack.
You're a united front now.
Toshiko, the poor girl who'll screw
any passing alien that gives her a pendant?
Owen, so strong, he gets in a cage with a Weevil,
desperate to be mauled.
Ianto, hiding his Cyber-girlfriend in the basement.
Your three comrades here
pumped bullets into her, remember?
I've got to get Rhys back.
Yeah, 'cause you're so in love with Rhys
that you spent half your time in Owen's bed.
Fuck you !
We're relieving you of your command, Captain !
We're opening that rift
and getting back what we lost!
-Shit!
-OWEN : Stay down !
You wanna be in charge, Owen?
You got to have significantly bigger balls.
I'm sick of people doubting me.
What have you done?
We've still got to do Jack's.
(ALARM BLARING)
(GROWLS)
(SCREAMING)
(GASPING)
Oh, my God.
What have you done?
Help me move him !
GWEN : Quick!
Go!
-OWEN : Keep moving.
-Right, Jack...
everything is going to go back to normal.
From out of the darkness, he is come.
What is he talking about?
Son of the Great Beast,
cast out before time, chained in rock
and imprisoned beneath the rift.
What?
All hail, Abaddon, the Great Devourer.
Come to feast on life.
(ROARING)
The whole world shall die beneath his shadow.
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
I look upon you, my God,
and know my work is done.
How do we stop it? Tell me what to do, Jack.
Just you, get me to an open space.
What are you gonna do?
If Abaddon is the bringer of death,
let's see how he does with me.
If he feeds on life,
then I'm an all-you-can-eat buffet.
No, wait! Wait, you're too weak!
Get out of here, go!
Drive as fast as you can.
Jack.
Bring it on !
(ROARING)
(SCREAMING)
(SOBBING)
-You're here!
-Weren't you just here a minute ago?
You're here.
Go to bed. Get some sleep and I'll be back for you.
You're certain?
He's ice cold.
No vital signs.
GWEN : He survived when you shot him.
When I first joined he said he couldn't die.
He was wrong.
I want to sit with him.
-Gwen...
-I want to sit with him.
Wake up.
Jack.
How long is she gonna do this?
It's been days.
We have to face up to it.
He's not coming back.
I believe in him.
Let him go, Gwen.
JACK: Thank you.
(CH UCKLES)
-I'm...
-I forgive you.
(CRYING)
What's happened to the rift?
It closed up when Abaddon was destroyed.
But it's gonna be more volatile than ever.
The visions we had. We all saw people we loved.
What did you see?
Nothing.
There was nothing.
Jack...
what would have tempted you?
What visions would've convinced you
to open the rift?
The right kind of doctor.
Jack...
Where are they with those coffees?
(ELECTRONIC BEEPING)
(WHOOSHING)
Jack.
Jack?
-Did you see Jack on your way in?
-No.
I thought we tidied up in here!
What's the matter?
He was just here.
Something's taken him. Jack's gone.